Chris Anderson: Perhaps we could start by just telling us about your country.
كريس أندرسون: ربما يمكننا البدء بأن تخبرنا عن بلدك.
It's three dots there on the globe. Those dots are pretty huge.
إنها 3 نقاط على الكرة الأرضية. وهي نقاط ضخمة جداً.
I think each one is about the size of California.
أعتقد أن كل واحدة منها بحجم كاليفورنيا.
Tell us about Kiribati.
أخبرنا عن كيريباتي.
Anote Tong: Well, let me first begin by saying how deeply grateful I am
أنوتي تونغ: حسنا، دعني أولًا أعبر عن مدى امتناني
for this opportunity to share my story with people who do care.
لمنحي الفرصة لمشاركة قصتي مع أشخاص مهتمين بسماعها.
I think I've been sharing my story with a lot of people who don't care too much.
فقد شاركت قصتي مع أشخاص كثر لا يبالون بها.
But Kiribati is comprised of three groups of islands:
تتألف كيريباتي من 3 مجموعات من الجزر:
the Gilbert Group on the west,
مجموعة جيلبرت في الغرب،
we have the Phoenix Islands in the middle,
ولدينا جزر فينيكس في الوسط،
and the Line Islands in the east.
وجزر الخط في الشرق.
And quite frankly, Kiribati is perhaps the only country
وبكل صراحة، أعتقد أن كيريباتي هي البلد الوحيد
that is actually in the four corners of the world,
الموجود في الزوايا الأربعة للعالم.
because we are in the Northern Hemisphere, in the Southern Hemisphere,
لأننا في النصف الشمالي والجنوبي للأرض،
and also in the east and the west of the International Date Line.
وأيضا شرق وغرب خط التاريخ الدولي.
These islands are entirely made up of coral atolls,
تتكون هذه الجزر بالكامل من أكاليل مرجانية،
and on average about two meters above sea level.
بمعدل ارتفاع مترين تقريبا فوق سطح البحر.
And so this is what we have.
وهذا كل ما لدينا.
Usually not more than two kilometers in width.
وفي العادة لا يزيد عرضها عن كيلومترين.
And so, on many occasions, I've been asked by people,
ويطرح عليَّ الناس فى مناسباتٍ عديدة هذا السؤال:
"You know, you're suffering, why don't you move back?"
"أنتم تُعانون، لماذا لا تتراجعون إلى عمق الجزر؟"
They don't understand.
إنهم لا يستوعبون
They have no concept of what it is that's involved.
لأنه ليست لديهم أية فكرة عن الأمر.
With the rising sea, they say, "Well, you can move back."
فيقولون مع ارتفاع سطح البحر، "يُمكنُكَم أن تتراجعوا إلى داخل الجزر."
And so this is what I tell them.
فأجيبهم قائلا:
If we move back, we will fall off on the other side of the ocean. OK?
لو تراجعنا، سنسقط في الجانب الآخر من المحيط، هل تفهمون؟
But these are the kinds of issues that people don't understand.
لكن هذا نوع من المشاكل التى لا يفهمها الناس
CA: So certainly this is just a picture of fragility there.
كريس: ومن المؤكد أنها صورة من صور الهشاشة هناك.
When was it that you yourself realized
متى أدركت
AT: Well, the story of climate change has been one that has been going on
أنتونى : إن قصة التغير المناخي كانت تتداول عندنا
for quite a number of decades.
منذ عقود عديدة.
And when I came into office in 2003,
وعندما أصبحت رئيساً سنة 2003،
I began talking about climate change at the United Nations General Assembly,
بدأت فى التحدث عن التغير المناخي في الجمعية العامة للأمم المتحدة.
but not with so much passion,
لكن ليس بالجدية اللازمة،
because then there was still this controversy among the scientists
لكون الجدال وقتها كان قائماً في أوساط العلماء
whether it was human-induced, whether it was real or it wasn't.
عما إذا كان التغير من صنع الإنسان، أو هل هو موجود حقاً أم لا.
But I think that that debate was fairly much concluded in 2007
لكن أظن أن الجدال قد حُسم سنة 2007
with the Fourth Assessment Report of the IPCC,
بصدور تقرير التقييم 4 للهيئة الحكومية الدولية المعنية بتغير المناخ
which made a categorical statement that it is real, it's human-induced,
مؤكدا بشكل قاطع أن الأمر حقيقى وأنه من صنع الإنسان،
and it's predicting some very serious scenarios
وتوقع بعض السيناريوهات الخطيرة جدًا
for countries like mine.
لبلدان مثل بلدي.
And so that's when I got very serious.
وعندها أصبحتُ جدياً أكثر في التعاطي مع الأمر.
In the past, I talked about it.
تحدثتُ عن هذا الأمر فى الماضي.
We were worried.
لقد كنا قلقين.
But when the scenarios, the predictions came in 2007,
لكن عندما أصبحت السيناريوهات والتوقعات حقيقة فى عام 2007،
it became a real issue for us.
أصبح الموضوع قضية مهمة لنا.
CA: Now, those predictions are, I think, that by 2100,
كريس: أظن أن تلك التوقعات تقول أنه بحلول عام 2100،
sea levels are forecast to rise perhaps three feet.
سيرتفع مستوى البحر إلى حوالي المتر.
There's scenarios where it's higher than that, for sure,
هناك سيناريوهات تُنبئ بارتفاع أكبر من ذلك، بالتأكيد،
but what would you say to a skeptic who said,
لكن ماذا تقول لمن يُشَكِّكُ قائلاً: "ما المقلق بارتفع البحر لمتر؟"
You're on average six feet above sea level.
فأنتم ترتفعون بمعدل مترين فوق سطح البحر.
What's the problem?"
"ما المشكلة فى ذلك؟"
AT: Well, I think it's got to be understood
أنوتى: حسنًا، من المهم أن نفهم
that a marginal rise in sea level
أن ارتفاعا هامشيا لمستوى البحر
would mean a loss of a lot of land,
يعني خسارة مساحة كبيرة من الأرض،
because much of the land is low.
لأن معظم الأرض تقع تحت مستوى البحر.
And quite apart from that, we are getting the swells at the moment.
وبغض النظر عن ذلك، فالأمواج اليوم ترتطم عند أقدامنا.
So it's not about getting two feet.
مما يعني أن الأمر غير مرتبط بالمترين.
I think what many people do not understand
أعتقد أن ما لا يستوعبه معظم الناس
is they think climate change is something that is happening in the future.
هو اعتقادهم بأن التغير المناخي هو أمر سيحدث في المستقبل.
Well, we're at the very bottom end of the spectrum.
والواقع، أننا نقف أسفل الدرج.
It's already with us.
إننا نعيش التغير المناخي.
We have communities who already have been dislocated.
لدينا مجتمعات أعيد توطينها بالفعل.
They have had to move, and every parliament session,
كان عليهم الرحيل، وفي كل جلسة برلمانية،
I'm getting complaints from different communities
أتلقى شكاوى من مختلف المجتمعات
asking for assistance to build seawalls,
تطلب المساعدة لبناء أسوار بحرية،
to see what we can do about the freshwater lens
وللنظر فيما يمكن القيام به حول عدسات المياه العذبة
because it's being destroyed,
فوضعيتها تتدهور،
and so in my trips to the different islands,
وخلال تنقلي بين الجزر المختلفة،
I'm seeing evidence of communities
أعاين وضعية مجتمعات
which are now having to cope with the loss of food crops,
عليها الآن التعامل مع خسارة محاصيلها الزراعية،
the contamination of the water lenses,
وتداخل مياه العدسات بمياه البحر،
and I see these communities perhaps leaving, having to relocate,
وقد أكون شاهداً على رحيل تلك المجتمعات، لأنه يجب عليها الانتقال من أرضها،
within five to 10 years.
من 5 إلى 10 أعوام.
CA: And then, I think the country suffered its first cyclone,
كريس: وبعدها، على ما أظن، تعرض البلد لأول إعصار في تاريخه،
and this is connected, yes? What happened here?
وهي أمور مرتبطة، أليس كذلك؟ ما الذي حدث؟
AT: Well, we're on the equator,
أنوتي: حسناً، نحن نقع على خط الاستواء،
and I'm sure many of you understand that when you're on the equator,
وأنا متأكد بأن معظمكم يعرف بأنه عندما تتواجدون على خط الاستواء،
it's supposed to be in the doldrums. We're not supposed to get the cyclones.
يفترض أننا في منطقة الركود، ولا يفترض أن نتعرض لأعاصير.
We create them, and then we send them either north or south.
نحن من يُكوَّن الأعاصير ومن ثم نرسلها نحو الشمال أو الجنوب.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But they aren't supposed to come back.
ولا يفترض بها العودة إلينا.
But for the first time, at the beginning of this year,
لكن ولأول مرة، في بداية هذه السنة،
the Cyclone Pam, which destroyed Vanuatu,
الإعصار بام، الذي دمر فانواتو،
and in the process, the very edges of it actually touched
وخلال تحركه، ضرب بأطرافه فقط
our two southernmost islands,
جزيرتان من جزرنا الواقعتان إلى أقصى الجنوب،
and all of Tuvalu was underwater when Hurricane Pam struck.
وكانت كامل تولوفا تحت الماء عندما ضربها إعصار بام.
But for our two southernmost islands,
وفي أقصى جزيرتين من جزرنا بالجنوب،
we had waves come over half the island,
كانت لدينا أمواج أتت على نصف الجزيرة،
and so this has never happened before.
وهذا لم يحدث قط من قبل.
It's a new experience.
كانت تلك تجربة جديدة لنا،
And I've just come back from my own constituency,
وأنا عائد للتو من دائرتي الانتخابية،
and I've seen these beautiful trees which had been there for decades,
وعاينت أشجارا جميلة كانت هناك منذ عقود،
they've been totally destroyed.
وهي مجتثة بالكامل.
So this is what's happening,
وهذا ما يحدث،
but when we talk about the rising sea level,
ولكن عندما نتحدث عن ارتفاع مستوى البحار،
we think it's something that happens gradually.
نعتقد بأنه أمر يحدث بتدرج.
It comes with the winds, it comes with the swells,
إنه يأتي مع الرياح ومع العباب
and so they can be magnified,
مما يزيد في حجمها،
but what we are beginning to witness is the change in the weather pattern,
ولكن ما نشهده الآن هو تغيير في نمط الطقس،
which is perhaps the more urgent challenge
وهو على الأرجح التحدي الأكثر إلحاحاً
that we will face sooner than perhaps the rising sea level.
الذي سنواجهه عما قريب وربما قبل ارتفاع مستوى البحار حتى.
CA: So the country is already seeing effects now.
كريس: إذاً فإن البلد يعيش الآن آثار التغير.
As you look forward,
باستشرافكم للمستقبل،
what are your options as a country, as a nation?
ما هي خياراتكم كبلد وكأمة؟
AT: Well, I've been telling this story every year.
أنوتي: أنا أروي هذه القصة كل سنة.
I think I visit a number of --
أظن أني زرت العديد من --
I've been traveling the world to try and get people to understand.
جبت العالم لأحاول جعل الناس تعي ذلك.
We have a plan, we think we have a plan.
أن لدينا خطة، ونعتقد بأن لدينا خطة.
And on one occasion, I think I spoke in Geneva
وخلال مناسبة، أعتقد في كلمة ألقيتها في جنيف
and there was a gentleman who was interviewing me
كان هناك رجل محترم أجرى معي مقابلة
on something like this,
حول أمر كهذا الموضوع،
and I said, "We are looking at floating islands,"
وقلت له: "نحن نبحث إمكانية الجزر العائمة"
and he thought it was funny, but somebody said,
وقد اعتقد أن الأمر مضحك ولكن شخصاً ما قال:
"No, this is not funny. These people are looking for solutions."
"لا، هذا ليس مضحكاً. هؤلاء الناس يبحثون عن حلول."
And so I have been looking at floating islands.
وعليه أنا أبحث إمكانية الجزر العائمة.
The Japanese are interested in building floating islands.
اليابانيون مهتمون بإنشاء الجزر العائمة.
But, as a country, we have made a commitment
ولكن، كبلد، التزامنا
that no matter what happens, we will try as much as possible
هو أنه بغض النظر عما سيحدث، سنحاول بقدر الإمكان
to stay and continue to exist as a nation.
البقاء والاستمرار في العيش كأمة.
What that will take,
وما سيتطلبه ذلك،
it's going to be something quite significant,
سيكون أمراً جد مهم،
very, very substantial.
جد، جد هام.
Either we live on floating islands,
سواء أكنا نعيش على جزر عائمة
or we have to build up the islands to continue to stay out of the water
أو كان علينا إنشاء الجزر للبقاء خارج المياه
as the sea level rises and as the storms get more severe.
مع ارتفاع مستوى البحار وشدة الأعاصير.
But even that, it's going to be very, very difficult
بل إن حتى هذا الأمر سيصعب كثيرا
to get the kind of resourcing that we would need.
أمر الحصول على الموارد التي سنحتاجها.
CA: And then the only recourse is some form of forced migration.
كريس: إذاً فإن الخيار الوحيد هو نوع من التهجير القسري.
AT: Well, we are also looking at that
أنوتي: نحن ندرس أيضاً هذا الخيار
because in the event that nothing comes forward
لأنه في حالة عدم توصل المجتمع الدولي
from the international community,
إلى حل،
we are preparing,
فإننا نستعد،
we don't want to be caught like what's happening in Europe.
فلا نرغب في أن نجد أنفسنا في ورطة كما حدث في أوروبا.
OK? We don't want to mass migrate at some point in time.
أليس كذلك؟ لا نريد الهجرة جماعياً في وقت ما.
We want to be able to give the people the choice today,
ونريد اليوم أن نكون قادرين على منح الناس إمكانية الاختيار،
those who choose and want to do that, to migrate.
أولئك الذين اختاروا وأرادوا الهجرة.
We don't want something to happen that they are forced to migrate
فلا نريد أن يحدث أمر ما يجبرهم على الهجرة القسرية
without having been prepared to do so.
دون الاستعداد لذلك.
Of course, our culture is very different, our society is very different,
وبالطبع، فإن ثقافتنا ومجتمعنا جد مختلفين،
and once we migrate into a different environment,
وعند هجرتنا إلى بيئة مختلفة
a different culture,
وثقافة مختلفة،
there's a whole lot of adjustments that are required.
فإن هناك العديد من التعديلات الضرورية للقيام بها.
CA: Well, there's forced migration in your country's past,
كريس: لقد عرف بلدكم هجرة قسرية في الماضي،
and I think just this week,
وأظن أنه في الأسبوع الماضي فقط،
just yesterday or the day before yesterday,
بالأمس فقط أو أول أمس،
you visited these people.
زرت أولئك الناس.
What happened here? What's the story here?
ما الذي حدث هناك؟ ما القصة هناك؟
AT: Yes, and I'm sorry, I think somebody was asking
أنوتي: نعم، وأنا آسف، أظن أن أحدهم تساءل
why we were sneaking off to visit that place.
لماذا اختفينا لزيارة ذاك المكان.
I had a very good reason, because we have a community of Kiribati people
كان لدي سبب وجيه، لأنه لدينا مجتمع من الكيريباتيين
living in that part of the Solomon Islands,
يعيشون في هذا الجزء من جزر سليمان،
but these were people who were relocated from the Phoenix Islands, in fact,
والواقع، أنهم كانوا مجتمعاً أعيد توطينهم هناك من جزر فينكس،
in the 1960s.
في الستينيات.
There was serious drought, and the people could not continue to live on the island,
كان هناك جفاف شديد ولم يعد بإمكان الناس الاستمرار في العيش على الجزيرة،
and so they were moved to live here in the Solomon Islands.
وبالتالي نُقلوا للعيش في جزر سليمان.
And so yesterday it was very interesting to meet with these people.
ومقابلة أولئك الناس بالأمس كان أمراً جد مهم.
They didn't know who I was. They hadn't heard of me.
لم يكونوا يعرفونني. ولم يسمعوا بي من قبل.
Some of them later recognized me,
وبعضهم تعرف عليَّ لاحقاً،
but I think they were very happy.
ولكن أعتقد أنهم كانوا سعداء.
Later they really wanted to have the opportunity to welcome me formally.
ولاحقاً، أرادوا أن تتاح لهم الفرصة لاستقبالي بشكل رسمي.
But I think what I saw yesterday was very interesting
لكن أظن أن ما شاهدته الأمس كان جد مهم
because here I see our people.
لأني شاهدت هناك شعبنا.
I spoke in our language, and of course they spoke back, they replied,
لقد تحدثت بلغتنا وبالطبع ردوا عليَّ
but their accent, they are beginning not to be able to speak Kiribati properly.
ولكن بلكنة، لقد أصبحوا غير قادرين على التحدث بلغة كيريباتية فصحى.
I saw them, there was this lady with red teeth.
زرتهم وكانت هناك امرأة بأسنان حمراء.
She was chewing betel nuts,
كانت تلوك التنبول،
and it's not something we do in Kiribati.
وهي ليست من عاداتنا في كيريباتي.
We don't chew betel nuts.
نحن لا نلوك التنبول.
I met also a family who have married the local people here,
وقد التقيت أيضاً أسرة تزوجت من السكان المحليين هناك،
and so this is what is happening.
وهذا ما يحدث حالياً.
As you go into another community, there are bound to be changes.
عندما تدخلون إلى مجتمع آخر، هناك حدود ستتغير في مجتمعكم.
There is bound to be a certain loss of identity,
وهناك حدود سنخسرها في هويتنا،
and this is what we will be looking for in the future
وهذا ما سنلاحظه في المستقبل
if and when we do migrate.
إذا أو عندما سنهاجر.
CA: It must have been just an extraordinarily emotional day
كريس: من الأكيد أنه كان يوما مليئا بالعواطف
because of these questions about identity,
بسبب تلك الأسئلة حول الهوية،
the joy of seeing you and perhaps an emphasized sense of what they had lost.
وفرحة لقائك وإدراكهم لما خسروه.
And it's very inspiring to hear you say you're going to fight to the end
ومن الملهم الاستماع إليك تقول بأنك ستناضل إلى النهاية
to try to preserve the nation in a location.
لمحاولة الحفاظ على الأمة في أرضها.
AT: This is our wish.
أنوتي: هذا ما نرجوه.
Nobody wants ever to leave their home,
فلا أحد يرغب في ترك منزله،
and so it's been a very difficult decision for me.
لهذا كان ذلك قرارا صعبا بالنسبة لي.
As a leader, you don't make plans to leave your island, your home,
كزعيم لا يكون من مخططاتك ترك جزيرتك ومنزلك،
and so I've been asked on a number of occasions,
وقد سئلت في العديد من المناسبات:
"So how do you feel?"
"ما هو إحساسك؟"
And it doesn't feel good at all.
ليس شعوري جيداً على الإطلاق.
It's an emotional thing, and I've tried to live with it,
إنه أمر عاطفي، وقد حاولت التأقلم معه،
and I know that on occasions, I'm accused of not trying to solve the problem
وأنا أعلم أني أتهم أحياناً بعدم محاولة حل المشكل
because I can't solve the problem.
والواقع أنه ليس بمقدوري حل المشكل.
It's something that's got to be done collectively.
فذلك أمرعلينا القيام به بشكل جماعي.
Climate change is a global phenomenon, and as I've often argued,
التغير المناخي هي ظاهرة عالمية، وكما أقول دائما،
unfortunately, the countries, when we come to the United Nations --
للأسف، الدول، عندما نأتي إلى الأمم المتحدة --
I was in a meeting with the Pacific Island Forum countries
شاركت في اجتماع مع دول منتدى جزر المحيط الهادئ
where Australia and New Zealand are also members,
حيث أستراليا ونيوزيلاندا عضوان أيضا،
and we had an argument.
وقد تجادلنا خلاله.
There was a bit of a story in the news
وقد كان لذلك صدى في الصحافة
because they were arguing that to cut emissions,
لأنهما عارضا فكرة وقف انبعاثات الغازات،
it would be something that they're unable to do
لأنه أمر لا يسعهما تطبيقه
because it would affect the industries.
لأن ذلك سيؤثر على الصناعات.
And so here I was saying,
وقد قلت آنذاك،
OK, I hear you,
حسنا، أنا أستمع إليكم،
I understand what you're saying,
وأتفهم ما تقصدانه،
but try also to understand what I'm saying
لكن حاولا أيضا تفهم ما أقوله
because if you do not cut your emissions,
لأنكما إذا لم توقفا انبعاثاتكما،
then our survival is on the line.
فإن بقاءنا أحياء على المحك.
And so it's a matter for you to weigh this, these moral issues.
وبالتالي عليكما تقدير هذا الأمر لأنها قضية أخلاقية.
It's about industry as opposed to the survival of a people.
فالأمر متعلق بالصناعة مقابل الحفاظ على حياة الناس.
CA: You know, I ask you yesterday what made you angry,
كريس: أتعلم، سألتك البارحة عما يغضبك،
and you said, "I don't get angry." But then you paused.
وقلت: "أنا لا أغضب." ولكن بعدها صمتت.
I think this made you angry.
أعتقد أن هذا ما يجعلك تغضب.
AT: I'd refer you to my earlier statement at the United Nations.
أنوتي: سأحيلك على كلمتي السابقة التي ألقيتها في الأمم المتحدة.
I was very angry, very frustrated and then depressed.
كنت جد غاضب ومحبط فأصبت بالكآبة.
There was a sense of futility
كان هناك نوع من العبث
that we are fighting a fight that we have no hope of winning.
لأننا نخوض معركة لا أمل لنا في الفوز بها.
I had to change my approach.
كان عليَّ تغيير منهاجي.
I had to become more reasonable
كان عليَّ أن أصبح أكثر واقعية
because I thought people would listen to somebody who was rational,
لأني اعتقدت أن الناس سيستمعون لشخص واقعي،
but I remain radically rational, whatever that is.
لكني كنت وما أزال واقعيا بتطرف، أيا كان ما أقوله.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: Now, a core part of your nation's identity is fishing.
كريس: جوهر هوية أمتك هو الصيد.
I think you said pretty much everyone is involved in fishing in some way.
وأعتقد أنك قلت بأن أغلب الناس مرتبطون بشكل أو بآخر بالصيد.
AT: Well, we eat fish every day, every day,
أنوتي: حسنا، نحن نأكل السمك كل يوم، كل يوم،
and I think there is no doubt that our rate of consumption of fish
وأعتقد بأنه لا شك بأن معدل استهلاكنا للسمك
is perhaps the highest in the world.
هو على الأرجح الأعلى في العالم.
We don't have a lot of livestock,
وليس لدينا مخزون كاف من الغذاء،
so it's fish that we depend on.
لذا فإننا نعتمد على السمك.
CA: So you're dependent on fish, both at the local level
كريس: إذا أنتم معتمدين على السمك سواء على المستوى المحلي
and for the revenues that the country receives
أو العوائد الخارجية للبلاد
from the global fishing business for tuna,
من التجارة العلمية لسمك التونة،
and yet despite that, a few years ago you took a very radical step.
ورغم ذلك، اتخذت قراراً جذرياً منذ بضع سنوات.
Can you tell us about that?
هلا أخبرتنا قليلا عن ذلك؟
I think something happened right here in the Phoenix Islands.
أعتقد أن أمرا ما حدث هنا على جزر فينكس.
AT: Let me give some of the background of what fish means for us.
أنوتي: دعني أخبركم قليلا عن معنى السمك بالنسبة لنا.
We have one of the largest tuna fisheries remaining in the world.
لدينا واحدة من أكبر صناعات سمك التونة المتبقية في العالم
In the Pacific, I think we own something like 60 percent
أعتقد أننا في المحيط الهادئ نملك ما يقارب 60%
of the remaining tuna fisheries,
مما تبقى من صناعة صيد التونة،
and it remains relatively healthy for some species, but not all.
وما زال الصيد مقبول بالنسبة لبعض الأنواع، لكن ليست كلها.
And Kiribati is one of the three major resource owners,
وكيريباتي هي إحدى الجزر الثلاثة التي تتوفر على مصادر مهمة،
tuna resource owners.
مصادر التونة.
And at the moment, we have been getting
وكنا إلى غاية اليوم، نحصل على
something like 80 to 90 percent of our revenue
ما يقارب 80 إلى 90% من عوائدنا
from access fees, license fees.
من رسوم الدخول والتراخيص للصيد.
CA: Of your national revenue.
كريس: من عوائدكم الوطنية.
AT: National revenue,
أنوتي: العوائد الوطنية،
which drives everything that we do
التي تحرك كل ما نقوم به
in governments, hospitals, schools and what have you.
في الحكومات والمستشفيات والمدارس وأمور أخرى.
But we decided to close this, and it was a very difficult decision.
لكننا قررنا إيقاف ذلك وكان قراراً صعباً.
I can assure you, politically, locally, it was not easy,
وأستطيع أن أؤكد لكم، أنه سياسيا ومحليا لم يكن الأمر سهلاً،
but I was convinced that we had to do this
لكني كنت أؤمن بأنه علينا القيام بذلك
in order to ensure that the fishery remains sustainable.
من أجل ضمان بقاء صناعة الصيد.
There had been some indications that some of the species,
فقد كانت هناك بعض المؤشرات على أن بعض الأنواع،
in particular the bigeye, was under serious threat.
ولاسيما التونة السندرية كانت ترزح تحت تهديد كبير.
The yellowfin was also heavily fished.
كما أنه تم اصطياد تونة الزعنفة الصفراء بشكل جائر.
Skipjack remains healthy.
ومازالت أعداد التونة الوثابة جيدة.
And so we had to do something like that, and so that was the reason I did that.
وبالتالي كان علينا اتخاذ قرار كهذا، وكان ذلك هو السبب في قراري ذاك.
Another reason why I did that
والسبب الآخر وراء قراري ذاك
was because I had been asking the international community
هو كوني كنت أطلب من المجتمع الدولي
that in order to deal with climate change, in order to fight climate change,
من أجل التعامل مع التغير المناخي، ومكافحته،
there has got to be sacrifice, there has got to be commitment.
القيام بتضحيات، وأن يكون هناك التزام.
So in asking the international community to make a sacrifice,
وعليه اعتقدت أنه إذا كنت أطالب المجتمع الدولي بالقيام بتضحيات،
I thought we ourselves need to make that sacrifice.
فسيكون علينا أيضا القيام بهذه التضحية.
And so we made the sacrifice.
وعليه قمنا بذلك.
And forgoing commercial fishing
والتخلي عن الصيد التجاري
in the Phoenix Islands protected area
في المنطقة المحمية من جزر فينكس
would mean a loss of revenue.
يعني خسارة العائد من ذلك النشاط.
We are still trying to assess what that loss would be
ومازلنا نحاول تقييم حجم الخسائر في المستقبل
because we actually closed it off at the beginning of this year,
لأننا أوقفنا الصيد التجاري مع بداية هذه السنة،
and so we will see by the end of this year
وسنرى ذلك مع نهاية هذه السنة
what it means in terms of the lost revenue.
وأقصد فيما يتعلق بالخسائر في العائد.
CA: So there's so many things playing into this.
كريس: إذا هناك الكثير من المغامرة في هذا الأمر.
On the one hand, it may prompt healthier fisheries.
فمن جهة، قد يعقلن ذلك القرار الصيد.
I mean, how much are you able to move the price up
أقصد، ما هي الزيادة التي يمكنكم فرضها
that you charge for the remaining areas?
للصيد بالمناطق الأخرى؟
AT: The negotiations have been very difficult,
أنوتي: المفاوضات كانت عسيرة،
but we have managed to raise the cost of a vessel day.
وقد توصلنا إلى رفع الرسم اليومي على سفن الصيد.
For any vessel to come in to fish for a day,
على أي سفينة تأتي لتصطاد هناك ليوم واحد،
we have raised the fee from -- it was $6,000 and $8,000,
وقد رفعنا الرسم الذي كان ما بين 6.000 و8.000 دولار،
now to $10,000, $12,000 per vessel day.
إلى 10.000 و12.000 دولارا حاليا عن كل يوم لكل سفينة.
And so there's been that significant increase.
وكانت تلك زيادة مهمة.
But at the same time, what's important to note is,
لكن في نفس الوقت، من المهم الإشارة إلى
whereas in the past these fishing boats
أنه في الماضي كان يمكن لتلك السفن
might be fishing in a day and maybe catch 10 tons,
أن تصطاد في اليوم 10 سمكات تونة،
now they're catching maybe 100 tons because they've become so efficient.
وحاليا قد تصطاد 100 سمكة لأن السفن أصبحت أكثر فاعلية.
And so we've got to respond likewise.
وعليه كان علينا التعامل مع الأمر بحكمة.
We've got to be very, very careful because the technology has so improved.
وكان علينا أن نكون جد حذرين، لأن تقنيات الصيد أصبحت جد متطورة.
There was a time when the Brazilian fleet moved from the Atlantic to the Pacific.
فقد تمكن أسطول الصيد البرازيلي في فترة ما من الانتقال من المحيط الأطلسي حتى الهادئ.
They couldn't.
عكس الماضي.
They started experimenting if they could, per se.
فبدأوا يقومون بتجارب لمعرفة ما إذا كان بإمكانهم ذلك.
But now they've got ways of doing it, and they've become so efficient.
لكن الآن أصبحت لديهم طرق للقيام بذلك وأصبحوا أكثر فعالية.
CA: Can you give us a sense of what it's like in those negotiations?
كريس: هلا أخبرتنا عما دار في المفاوضات؟
Because you're up against companies
لأنك في الأساس ضد الشركات
that have hundreds of millions of dollars at stake, essentially.
ذات المئات الملايين من الدولارات.
How do you hold the line?
كيف تتحمل الإغراء؟
Is there any advice you can give
هل لديك نصيحة تود تقديمها
to other leaders who are dealing with the same companies
لباقي الزعماء الذين يواجهون نفس الشركات
about how to get the most for your country,
حول كيفية الحصول على الأفضل لبلدك،
get the most for the fish?
وللأسماك؟
What advice would you give?
ما النصيحة التي يمكنك تقديمها؟
AT: Well, I think we focus too often on licensing
أنوتي: حسنا، أعتقد أننا نركز كثيرا على منح رخص
in order to get the rate of return,
من أجل الحصول على معدل العائد،
because what we are getting from license fees
لأن ما نحصل عليه من رسوم الرخص
is about 10 percent of the landed value of the catch
هو حوالي 10% من قيمة الصيد الذي يصل إلى البر
on the side of the wharf, not in the retail shops.
على الرصيف، وليس في المحلات.
And we only get about 10 percent.
ونحصل فقط على حوالي 10%.
What we have been trying to do over the years
وقد حاولنا في الواقع خلال السنوات الأخيرة
is actually to increase our participation in the industry,
الرفع من مساهمتنا في الصناعة،
in the harvesting, in the processing,
والصيد والتصنيع
and eventually, hopefully, the marketing.
وفي النهاية، نرجو ذلك، التسويق.
They're not easy to penetrate,
وهي مجالات من الصعب اقتحامها،
but we are working towards that,
لكننا نعمل في هذا المنحى،
and yes, the answer would be to enhance.
ونعم، سيكون الجواب من أجل تعزيز العرض.
In order to increase our rate of return, we have to become more involved.
فلرفع معدل العائد، سيكون علينا أن نصبح أكثر تطورا.
And so we've started doing that,
وهذا ما بدأنا في القيام به،
and we have to restructure the industry.
وعلينا أن نعيد هيكلة صناعة الصيد.
We've got to tell these people that the world has changed.
وأن نخبر الناس بأن العالم تغير.
Now we want to produce the fish ourselves.
فنحن الآن نريد إنتاج السمك بأنفسنا.
CA: And meanwhile, for your local fishermen,
كريس: وماذا عن الصيادين المحليين،
they are still able to fish,
مازال بإمكانهم الصيد،
but what is business like for them?
ولكن ما وضعية نشاطهم اليوم؟
Is it getting harder? Are the waters depleted?
هل ازداد تعقيدا؟ هل اختفت الأسماك في مناطق صيدهم؟
Or is that being run on a sustainable basis?
أم أنهم يعملون بشكل مستدام؟
AT: For the artisanal fishery,
أنوتي: بالنسبة للصيادين التقليديين، نحن لا نساهم في النشاط التجاري للصيد
except only to supply the domestic market.
إلا في حالة تزويد السوق المحلية.
The tuna fishery is really entirely for the foreign market,
ويوجه إنتاج صناعة صيد سمك التونة بالكامل للسوق الخارجية،
mostly here in the US, Europe, Japan.
ومعظمه إلى الولايات المتحدة وأوروبا واليابان.
So I am a fisherman, very much,
أنا صياد، بمعنى الكلمة،
and I used to be able to catch yellowfin.
واعتدت أن أصطاد تونة الزعنفة الصفراء.
Now it's very, very rare to be able to catch yellowfin
والآن أصبح من النادر اصطيادها
because they are being lifted out of the water by the hundreds of tons
لأنها اصطيدت بالمئات من الأطنان
by these purse seiners.
بواسطة الشباك الجرافة.
CA: So here's a couple of beautiful girls from your country.
كريس: هاتين طفلتين جميلتين من بلادك.
I mean, as you think about their future,
أقصد، وأنت تفكر في مستقبلهما،
what message would you have for them
ما الرسالة التي توجهها لهما
and what message would you have for the world?
وما الرسالة التي توجهها للعالم؟
AT: Well, I've been telling the world that we really have to do something
أنوتي: حسنا، دائما ما قلت للعالم أنه علينا حقا القيام بأمر ما
about what is happening to the climate
حول ما يحدث للمناخ
because for us, it's about the future of these children.
لأنه بالنسبة لنا، ذلك متعلق بمستقبل أولئك الأطفال.
I have 12 grandchildren, at least.
لدي 12 حفيدا على الأقل.
I think I have 12, my wife knows.
أعتقد أن لدي 12 حفيدا، زوجتي من يعرف ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I think I have eight children.
وأعتقد أن لدي 8 أبناء.
It's about their future.
والأمر متعلق بمستقبلهم.
Every day I see my grandchildren, about the same age as these young girls,
في كل يوم تقع عيني على أحفادي الذين هم أيضا في سن هاتين الفتاتين،
and I do wonder,
أتساءل،
and I get angry sometimes, yes I do.
وأغضب أحيانا، نعم أغضب.
I wonder what is to become of them.
أتساءل ما الذي سيحدث لهم.
And so it's about them
لذا فإنه من أجلهم
that we should be telling everybody,
علينا أن نخبر كل فرد في العالم،
that it's not about their own national interest,
بأن الأمر لا يتعلق بمصالح بلدانهم،
because climate change, regrettably, unfortunately,
لأن العديد من البلدان تعتبر،
is viewed by many countries as a national problem. It's not.
التغيير المناخي مع الأسف مشكلا وطنيا. وذلك خطأ.
And this is the argument we got into recently with our partners,
وكان هذا هو موضوع جدالنا الأخير مع شركائنا،
the Australians and New Zealanders,
الأستراليين والنيوزيلانديين،
because they said, "We can't cut any more."
لأنهم يقولون: "لا يمكننا إيقاف الانبعاثات بعد الآن."
This is what one of the leaders, the Australian leader, said,
وكان هذا ما قاله أحد الزعماء الأستراليين،
that we've done our part, we are cutting back.
لقد قمنا بحصتنا وأوقفنا الانبعاثات.
I said, What about the rest? Why don't you keep it?
فقلت: وماذا عن الحصة المتبقية؟ لماذا لا تحتفظون بها؟
If you could keep the rest of your emissions
إذا كان بإمكانكم الاحتفاظ ببقية انبعاثاتكم
within your boundaries, within your borders,
داخل حدودكم،
we'd have no question.
فلن يكون هناك إشكال.
You can go ahead as much as you like.
يمكنكم أن تفعلوا كل ما تريدون.
But unfortunately, you're sending it our way,
لكن للأسف، أنتم ترسلونها نحونا،
and it's affecting the future of our children.
وهي تؤثر على مستقبل أطفالنا.
And so surely I think that is the heart of the problem of climate change today.
وأنا أعتقد أن هذا هو جوهر قضية التغير المناخي اليوم.
We will be meeting in Paris at the end of this year,
سنجتمع في باريس في أواخر هذه السنة،
but until we can think of this as a global phenomenon,
لكن وإلى أن ننظر إلى الأمر على أنه ظاهرة عالمية،
because we create it, individually, as nations,
لأننا جعلنا منها قضية خاصة بكل وطن على حدة،
but it affects everybody else,
فإنها تؤثر على الجميع،
and yet, we refuse to do anything about it,
ومع ذلك نرفض القيام بأي شيء حيالها،
and we deal with it as a national problem,
ونتعامل معها كقضية وطنية،
which it is not -- it is a global issue,
وهي ليست كذلك -- إنها قضية عالمية،
and it's got to be dealt with collectively.
ينبغي التعامل معها بشكل جماعي.
CA: People are incredibly bad at responding to graphs and numbers,
كريس: الناس تتفاعل بشكل سيء مع الرسوم البيانية والأرقام،
and we shut our minds to it.
ونغلق عقولنا أمامها.
Somehow, to people, we're slightly better at responding to that sometimes.
لكن عندما يتعلق الأمر بالناس يكون تفاعلنا أفضل أحيانا.
And it seems like it's very possible that your nation,
ويبدو أنه من الممكن أن تشكل أمتك،
despite, actually because of the intense problems you face,
بالرغم، أو بسبب المشاكل الكبيرة التي تواجهها،
you may yet be the warning light to the world that shines most visibly,
جرس الإنذار الذي لا يمكن للعالم
most powerfully.
أن يصم أذانه عنه،
I just want to thank you, I'm sure, on behalf of all of us,
وأود فقط أن أشكرك، باسمنا جميعا.
for your extraordinary leadership and for being here.
لقيادتك الرائعة ولحضورك معنا هنا.
Mr. President, thank you so much.
شكرا لك سيدي الرئيس.
AT: Thank you.
أنوتي: شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)